Guide to the Shaare Torah Congregation, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1936-1996 AIS.1998.22
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shaare Torah Congregation, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1936-1996
1940-1993
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shaare Torah Congregation (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1998.22
12.5 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
The Shaare Torah Congregation was founded in 1880 by Orthodox Jewish immigrants to Pittsburgh. The first permanent synagogue for the congregation was built in 1909, and longtime Rabbi Bernard A. Poupko was installed in 1943. This collection contains records of Shaare Torah from Rabbi Poupko's tenure and slightly before, including records of membership, programs hosted by the congregation, and cemetery records.
History
The Shaare Torah Congregation was founded in 1880 by Orthodox Jewish immigrants to Pittsburgh during the city's industrial expansion. Most of the founders came from eastern Europe. Several buildings were used as meeting places through the first years of the congregation until the first permanent synagogue was built in 1909.
Rabbi Moshe Simon Sivitz served the congregation from 1881 until his death in 1936. After this loss visiting Rabbis occupied the pulpit until January 10, 1943, when Rabbi Bernard A. Poupko was installed. On April 20, 1947, ground was broken for the congregation's current building at the intersection of Murray and Nicholson Avenues in the Squirrel Hill neighborhood of Pittsburgh.
Since its founding, Shaare Torah Congregation has been an active center for worship, learning, and culture. It has undertaken many philanthropic efforts in the local Jewish community, such as establishing an annual scholarship to Yeshiva University and Hillel Academy and contributing to other Jewish institutions of higher learning in the United States and Israel. Shaare Torah is a member of the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America.
More information about Shaare Torah's current activity can be found on their Web site: http://www.shaaretorah.net/index.php.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains records of Shaare Torah from 1936-1993, including records of membership, programs hosted by the congregation, and burials of deceased members. The records are divided into seven series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1965-1970
Series II. Membership
Series III. Programs and Publications
Series IV. Minutes and By-laws, 1949-1957
Series V. Cemetery Records
Series VI. Record Books
Series VII. Scrapbooks, 1940-1993
Additional scope notes are found at the series level. A commemorative book published in 1955 and offering more details of the congregation's history can be found in Series III.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Shaare Torah Congregation, Pittsburgh, Pa., in 1998.
Previous Citation
Shaare Torah Congregation, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1936-1996, AIS.1998.22, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Rabbis -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Ethnic groups; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Churches and Synagogues; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- History; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Social conditions; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Social life and customs; Orthodox Judaism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Synagogues -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Hillel Academy (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Poupko, Bernard A.; Shaare Torah Congregation (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Sivitz, M. S.; Yeshiva University
- Correspondence, 1965-1970; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series predominantly consists of letters from the executive secretary to members of the congregation. There are also letters between Shaare Torah personnel and other agencies. Most letters to individual congregation members deal with matters such as condolences for deaths, donations, and tuition for the Hebrew school.
  - 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
  - Letters to Entire Congregation (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Donations, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Membership Records, II.
  Men's membership records contain the names of the men who belonged to the congregation, their addresses, and their dues owed and paid per year. The cards in Box 3 are organized in alphabetical order. They contain the names and addresses of both male and female members of the congregation.
  - Men's Membership, A-Z (Box 2, Folder 1-19)
  - Membership Cards, A-K (Box 3)
- Programs and Publications, III.
  Besides regular worship and holiday observances, Shaare Torah has hosted a Hebrew school, ongoing educational programs, an annual banquet, and other social events. This series contains programs of the annual banquets; graduation exercises and other school ceremonies; and fundraising events such as the annual donor luncheon of the Shaare Torah Sisterhood, which celebrated each years's fundraising campaign undertaken by the women of Shaare Torah. The series also contains annual reports of receipts, various writings of Rabbi Poupko and isolated issues of a few periodicals.
  - Annual Banquets, Programs, 1955-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1-8)
  - Kollel Bais Yitchok (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Shaare Torah Religious School - Graduation Exercises, 1951-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Shaare Torah Hebrew School - Bas Mitzvah Ceremonies, 1964-1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Yeshiva Achei Tmimim, 1977, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Poale Zedck Congregation, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Hillel Academy of Pittsburgh (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - American Zionist Fund Dinners (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Shaare Torah Sisterhood Donor Luncheons, 1959-1981 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Other Miscellaneous Events (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Schedule of Upcoming Events, 1972-1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Shaare Torah Adult Institute - Schedule of Lectures and Reviews by Dr. Poupko, 1969-1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Hillel Campaign Solicitation Prospects (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Moat Chitim Fund Roster, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Tickets to Holiday Services, 1959, 1969, 1973, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Writings of Rabbi Poupko, 1964, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - American Jewish Outlook, Aug 26 and Nov 25, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - The Jewish Criterion - Shaare Torah 75th Anniversary Issue, Dec 2, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Annual Reports: Receipts, 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 30-34)
  - Anniversary Journal - Memorial Receipts (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - The 613 Commandments (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Seating for a Banquet, c1961 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Pages from a boy's Hebrew school notebook (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lists (Membership, Committees, etc.) (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Men's Club (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 41-45)
  - Memorabilia (Box 5 (Oversize))
- Minutes and By-laws, 1949-1957; IV.
  Most of the minutes in this series are from the board of directors meetings, which occur approximately once a month, but some are from general membership or special meetings. All minutes are written in English except for a bound volume covering most of 1949, which is written in Yiddish. Bound preservation copies will be used by researchers for the minutes kept from late 1949 to 1954. Bound volumes and unbound pages of minutes are housed in oversized flat boxes.
  - Minutes of Board of Directors/Committee Meetings, 1956-1957 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 1)
  - By-laws/Charter of Congregation (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1954-1957 (Box 6 (Oversize), Volume 1)
  - Minutes, 1949-1954 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 3)
  - Minutes, (Bound Preservation Copies), 1949-1954 (Box 6 (Oversize), Volume 2)
  - Minutes, 1949 (Box 6 (Oversize), Volume 3)
- Cemetery Records, V.
  Shaare Torah maintains a cemetery at 861 Stewart Ave. near Overbrook in the South Hills area of Pittsburgh. Records in this series consist of correspondence, reports, and receipts regarding the establishment and maintenance of burial plots and monuments; and two bound volumes listing the locations of burial plots.
  - Correspondence, 1965-1970 (Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Cemetery Records, B-Z, 1948-1957 (Box 7, Folder 13-20)
  - Cemetery Records, Miscellaneous, c1950-1954 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Maintenance, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Cemetery Maintenance Receipts, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Cemetery Book: A-T, Upper and Lower Sections, undated (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Cemetery Book: T-Z, AA-ZZ and AAA, undated (Box 9, Volume 2)
- Record Books, VI.
  Bound record books include records of seating and cash transactions. Several of them are written in Yiddish, and not all of their contents have been identified. A more detailed inventory of these books is available in a folder in Box 10.
  - Record Books (Box 10 (Oversize))
  - Record Books (Box 11)
  - Record Books (Box 12 (Oversize))
- Scrapbooks, 1940-1993; VII.
  Eight scrapbooks filled with newspaper clippings about the congregation and its activities from 1952 to 1996 are housed in flat boxes.
  - 1952-1957 (Box 13 (Oversize), Volume 1-2)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 14 (Oversize), Volume 3-4)
  - 1959-1987 (Box 15 (Oversize), Volume 5-6)
  - 1987-1996 (Box 16 (Oversize), Volume 7-8)